<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>

<job>
	<title>Researcher in Drilling Mechanics and Dynamics</title>
	<company id="hcc"/>
	<daterange>
		<from>
			<date month="January" monthnumber="1" year="2006"/>
		</from>
		<to>
			<date month="November" monthnumber="11" year="2013"/>
		</to>
╨	</daterange>
	<description>
		<p>Conducted research in drilling mechanics and dynamics.</p>
		<bulletedlist>
			<item>
				Developed a computer model used to predict the transient dynamic behavior of drill bits.
				<bulletedlist>
					<item>
						Over 70k lines of C++ with a Qt UI and a custom physics and computational geometry engine.
						<!-- In this approach, the known physics are captured by physical models.  The unknown physics are modeled using machine learning techniques. -->
					</item>
					<item>
						The model uses a hybrid physics and data-driven approach to predict behavior.
						<!-- In this approach, the known physics are captured by physical models.  The unknown physics are modeled using machine learning techniques. -->
					</item>
					<item>
						<!-- HPC -->
						The code was optimized using multithreading and high-performance computing techniques.
					</item>
					<item>
						Oversaw the physics models, software design and architecture, and project management, ensuring software accuracy, timely deliverables,
						and adherence to budget, resulting in efficient project execution.
					</item>
					<item>Developed a technique to reduce the cost of model fitting by an order of magnitude.</item>
					<item>Transferred development to an overseas-based software team and managed them.</item>
				</bulletedlist>
			</item>
			<item>
				Conducted research that led to an improved theoretical understanding of lateral drill bit vibrations, which I used to develop novel techniques for
				designing drill bits.  This enabled direct bit design, reducing reliance on trial-and-error methods.
			</item>
			<item>Developed a technique used to interpret laboratory data.  The technique is a physics-based approach that replaced the previous assumption-based method.</item>
		</bulletedlist>
	</description>
</job>