<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>

<experience>
	<job>
		<title>Principal Engineer</title>
		<company id="aps-houston"/>
		<daterange>
			<from>
				<date month="January" monthnumber="1" year="2014"/>
			</from>
			<to>Current</to>
		</daterange>
		<description>
			<p>Areas of work included drilling dynamics, drilling optimization, and data analysis.</p>
			<bulletedlist>
				<item>
					Conducted an in-depth review of a proprietary drilling dynamics tool that uses magnetorheological fluid to adjust the damping properties of the tool.  Review included sensor capabilities, calculations performed by the firmware, data produced, control algorithms, dynamic behavior, and operational usage.  The conclusions were documented and recommendations made on how to proceed with further testing and development of the device.
				</item>
				<item>
					Developed an FEA based software that calculates deflections, stresses, natural frequencies, and mode shapes of a drill string.  The software is used to assess the bending capabilities and stress limits of tools and drill strings for use in directional drilling applications.  It is also used to ensure natural frequencies are not excited (avoid resonance) and to assess changes in mode shapes that occur from different tool designs.
				</item>
				<item>
					Developed specialized data processing techniques and algorithms used to automate cleaning and processing of drilling data.  The software removes corrupted data points and separates the data into drilling versus non-drilling (standby) time.  Reduced the process from an hour to a minute.
				</item>
				<item>
					Developed generalized plotting software designed to work with data from any downhole tool.  Software is immune to changes in firmware, easily adaptable to new tools, has error handling for corrupted data, and automatic conversion of units.  The industry lacks standards for data handling, so similar data is often stored differently, even within a company.  Before I solved this issue, three others at APS had tried and failed to find a maintainable solution.  Updates and new product introduction eventually rendered all previous attempts obsolete.
				</item>
			</bulletedlist>
		</description>
	</job>
	
	<job>
        <title>Researcher in Drilling Mechanics and Dynamics</title>
        <company id="hcc"/>
        <daterange>
            <from>
                <date month="January" monthnumber="1" year="2006"/>
            </from>
            <to>
				<date month="November" monthnumber="11" year="2013"/>
            </to>
        </daterange>
        <description>
			<p>
				Conducted research in the areas of drilling mechanics and dynamics.  Work included developing theoretical understandings of drilling behavior, designing laboratory experiments, and developing computer models to predict drilling behavior.
			</p>
			<bulletedlist>
				<item>
					Developed an advanced, proprietary computational dynamics application used to predict and analyze the dynamic behavior of drill bits.  Was responsible for implementation and accuracy of physics, software design and architecture, algorithms, project schedule, deliverables, and budget.
				</item>
				<!--<item>Served as team member on project with objective to advance understanding of torsional and lateral drilling dynamics through a series of computer, laboratory, and full scale drill rig experiments.</item>-->
				<item>Developed a laboratory analysis technique to improve understanding of lateral bit dynamics.  The technique is a physics based approach that replaced the previous assumption based method.  The new method let engineers better interpret the results of laboratory tests.</item>
				<item>Improved theoretical understanding of lateral drill bit vibrations.  Used this understanding to create new techniques for designing drill bits.  These techniques let engineers design bits directly rather than requiring hundreds of computer simulations to find a solution.</item>
				<item>Designed and oversaw running of experiments in laboratory setting and on a full scale drill rig.</item>
				<item>Analyzed and interpreted computer, laboratory, and drill rig data.</item>
				<item>Developed software to post process a variety of disjointed laboratory and computer data types in a standardized, uniform way.</item>
				<item>Lead a software development team based in Russia.</item>
				<item>Trained new employees and directed the work of interns.</item>
				<item>Served as a member of a cross-divisional numerical modeling and simulation committee.</item>
			</bulletedlist>
        </description>
    </job>
    <!--<job>
        <title>Structural Engineer</title>
        <company id="burkettwong"/>
        <daterange>
            <from>
                <date month="August" monthnumber="8" year="2005"/>
            </from>
            <to>
                <date month="January" monthnumber="1" year="2006"/>
            </to>
        </daterange>
        <description>
            <p>Performed load calculations, checked drawings.</p>
        </description>
    </job>
    <job>
        <title>Graduate Student Researcher</title>
        <company id="ucsd"/>
        <daterange>
            <from>
                <date month="September" monthnumber="9" year="2002"/>
            </from>
            <to>
				<date month="December" monthnumber="12" year="2005"/>
            </to>
        </daterange>
        <description>
            <p>Performed research in the area of computational mechanics and numerical integration.</p>
        </description>
    </job>
    <job>
        <title>Teaching Assistant</title>
        <company id="ucsd"/>
        <daterange>
            <from>
                <date month="September" monthnumber="9" year="2001"/>
            </from>
            <to>
                <date month="June" monthnumber="6" year="2002"/>
            </to>
        </daterange>
        <description>
            <p>
				Wrote exams, graded homework and exams, held office hours, and lectured classes when the professor
				was unavailable.  Specifically requested by several students to be their T.A.\ because of 
				performance as their T.A.\ in a prior class.
			</p>
        </description>
    </job>
	<job>
        <title>C.A.D. Manager</title>
        <company id="ses"/>
        <daterange>
            <from>
                <date month="November" monthnumber="11" year="1998"/>
            </from>
            <to>
                <date month="September" monthnumber="9" year="2000"/>
            </to>
        </daterange>
        <description>
            <p>
				Created high quality, professional engineering drawings, conducted training, established 
				and maintained C.A.D. standards, and wrote productivity software for AutoCAD.
			</p>
        </description>
    </job>
    <job>
        <title>C.A.D. Operator</title>
        <company id="sed"/>
        <daterange>
            <from>
                <date month="June" monthnumber="6" year="1996"/>
            </from>
            <to>
                <date month="November" monthnumber="11" year="1998"/>
            </to>
        </daterange>
        <description></description>
    </job>-->
</experience>