<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>

<experience>
	<job>
		<title>Founder and President</title>
		<company id="ikosy"/>
		<daterange>
			<from>
				<date month="March" monthnumber="3" year="2021"/>
			</from>
			<to>Current</to>
		</daterange>
		<description>
			<p>Founded Ikosy Technologies to bring easy-to-use desktop pick-and-place technology to the maker community.</p>
			<bulletedlist>
				<item>
					Identified the business opportunity and formulated the business plan.
				</item>
				<item>
					Designed a desktop-sized pick-and-place machine.
				</item>
				<item>
					Recruited and lead a team of founders.
				</item>
			</bulletedlist>
		</description>
	</job>
	<job>
		<title>Principal Engineer</title>
		<company id="aps-houston"/>
		<daterange>
			<from>
				<date month="January" monthnumber="1" year="2014"/>
			</from>
			<to>
				<date month="June" monthnumber="6" year="2020"/>
			</to>
		</daterange>
		<description>
			<p>Areas of work included developing engineering software, data analysis, and drilling dynamics.\nolinebreak[4]</p>
			<bulletedlist>
				<item>
					Developed an FEA based software used for structural analysis of drill strings.
				</item>
				<bulletedlist>
					<item>
						The software calculates deflections, stresses, natural frequencies, and mode shapes.
					</item>
					<item>
						The software is used to assess the bending capabilities and stress limits of drill strings and assess the consequences of design changes.
					</item>
				</bulletedlist>
				<item>
					Developed a software application used to automate the cleaning and processing of data.
				</item>
				<bulletedlist>
					<item>
						The software uses specialized data processing techniques and algorithms to automatically separate the data into drilling versus non-drilling time (up time versus down time).
					</item>
				</bulletedlist>					
						

				<item>
					Developed generalized plotting software which can be configured for any type of input data.
				</item>
				<bulletedlist>
					<item>
						The input data came from a wide variety of sources that each had their own data format (syntax, organization, content, units of measurements).  Software architecture
						was used to generalize the process and handle all the data sources in an organized way.
					</item>
					<item>
						The software is capable of handling corrupt data and conversion of units.
					</item>
				</bulletedlist>
			</bulletedlist>
		</description>
	</job>
	
	<job>
        <title>Researcher in Drilling Mechanics and Dynamics</title>
        <company id="hcc"/>
        <daterange>
            <from>
                <date month="January" monthnumber="1" year="2006"/>
            </from>
            <to>
				<date month="November" monthnumber="11" year="2013"/>
            </to>
        </daterange>
		<description>
			<p>
				Conducted research in the areas of drilling mechanics and dynamics.  Work included developing theoretical understandings of drilling behavior, designing laboratory experiments, and developing computer models to predict drilling behavior.
			</p>
			<bulletedlist>
				<item>
					Developed a proprietary computer model used to predict the dynamic behavior of drill bits.
					<bulletedlist>
						<item>
							Responsibilities included the physics, software design and architecture, algorithms, project schedule, deliverables, and budget.
						</item>
						<item>
							The software models the physics of a drill bit removing rock material.
						</item>
						<item>
							The software is multi-threaded.  I created a technique to automatically avoid race conditions and deadlocks without requiring extensive use of mutexes.
						</item>
						<item>
							The physics model is calibrated to laboratory data by solving the inverse problem.  I developed a technique to reduce the cost of solving by an order of magnitude.
						</item>
						<item>Led a Russia based software development team.</item>
					</bulletedlist>
				</item>
				<item>My research led to an improved theoretical understanding of lateral drill bit vibrations.  I used this understanding to create new techniques for designing drill bits.  <italic>These techniques let engineers design bits directly rather than requiring hundreds of computer simulations that randomly searched for a solution.</italic>  This saved time and money.</item>
				<item>Developed a technique used to interpret laboratory data.  The technique is a physics-based approach that replaced the previous assumption-based method.</item>
			</bulletedlist>
		</description>
    </job>
	
</experience>