<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>

<experience>
	<job>
		<title>Founder and President</title>
		<company id="ikosy"/>
		<daterange>
			<from>
				<date month="March" monthnumber="3" year="2021"/>
			</from>
			<to>Current</to>
		</daterange>
		<description>
			<p>Founded Ikosy Technologies to bring easy to use desktop pick-and-place technology to the maker community.</p>
			<bulletedlist>
				<item>
					Identified the business opportunity and formulated the business plan.
				</item>
				<item>
					Recruited a team of founders who each bring a unique skill set.
				</item>
				<item>
					Designed a desktop-sized pick-and-place machine.
				</item>
			</bulletedlist>
		</description>
	</job>
	<job>
		<title>Principal Engineer</title>
		<company id="aps-houston"/>
		<daterange>
			<from>
				<date month="January" monthnumber="1" year="2014"/>
			</from>
			<to>
				<date month="June" monthnumber="6" year="2020"/>
			</to>
		</daterange>
		<description>
			<p>Areas of work included drilling dynamics, drilling optimization, and data analysis.</p>
			<bulletedlist>
				<item>
					Developed an FEA based software that calculates deflections, stresses, natural frequencies, and mode shapes of a drill string.  The software is used to assess the bending capabilities and stress limits of tools and drill strings, ensure natural frequencies are not excited, and assess the consequences of design changes.
					<!--<bulletedlist>
						<item>The software is used to assess the bending capabilities and stress limits of tools and drill strings.</item>
						<item>It is also used to ensure natural frequencies are not excited (avoid resonance) and to assess changes in mode shapes that occur from different tool designs.</item>
					</bulletedlist>-->
				</item>
				<item>
					Developed specialized data processing techniques and algorithms used to automate the cleaning and processing of drilling data.  The software removes corrupted data points and separates the data into drilling versus non-drilling time.  <italic>Reduced the process from an hour to a minute.</italic>
					<!--Developed specialized data processing techniques and algorithms used to automate cleaning and processing of drilling data.
					<bulletedlist>
						<item>The software detects removes corrupted data points.</item>
						<item>Drilling versus non-drilling (standby) time is automatically detected and separated.</item>
						<item><italic>Reduced the process from an hour to a minute.</italic></item>
					</bulletedlist>-->
				</item>
				<item>
					Developed generalized plotting software designed to work with data from any downhole tool.  Software is immune to changes in firmware, easily adaptable to new tools, has error handling for corrupted data, and automatic conversion of units.  The industry lacks standards for data handling, so similar data is often stored differently, even within a company.  <bold>Before I solved this issue, three others had tried and failed to find a solution.</bold>
				</item>
				<!--<item>
					Conducted an in-depth review of a proprietary drilling dynamics tool that uses magnetorheological fluid to adjust the damping properties of the tool.  Review included sensor capabilities, calculations performed by the firmware, data produced, control algorithms, dynamic behavior, and operational usage.  The conclusions were documented and recommendations made on how to proceed with further testing and development of the device.
				</item>-->
			</bulletedlist>
		</description>
	</job>
	
	<job>
        <title>Researcher in Drilling Mechanics and Dynamics</title>
        <company id="hcc"/>
        <daterange>
            <from>
                <date month="January" monthnumber="1" year="2006"/>
            </from>
            <to>
				<date month="November" monthnumber="11" year="2013"/>
            </to>
        </daterange>
		<description>
			<p>
				Conducted research in the areas of drilling mechanics and dynamics.  Work included developing theoretical understandings of drilling behavior, designing laboratory experiments, and developing computer models to predict drilling behavior.
			</p>
			<bulletedlist>
				<item>
					Developed an advanced, proprietary computer model used to predict and analyze the dynamic behavior of drill bits.  Was responsible for the physics, software design and architecture, algorithms, project schedule, deliverables, and budget.
					<bulletedlist>
						<item>
							The software models the physics of a drill bit removing rock material.
						</item>
						<item>
							The software is multi-threaded to speed up the simulation through parallelization.  I created a clever technique to automatically avoid race conditions and deadlocks without requiring extensive use of mutexes.
						</item>
						<item>
							The physics model is calibrated to laboratory data by solving the inverse problem.  <bold>I developed a technique to reduce the cost of solving by an order of magnitude.</bold>
						</item>
						<item>Lead the Russia based software development team.</item>
					</bulletedlist>
				</item>
				<item>Improved theoretical understanding of lateral drill bit vibrations.  Used this understanding to create new techniques for designing drill bits.  <italic>These techniques let engineers design bits directly rather than requiring hundreds of computer simulations that randomly searched for a solution.</italic>  This saved time and money.</item>
				<item>Developed a technique used to interpret laboratory data.  The technique is a physics-based approach that replaced the previous assumption-based method.</item>
				<item>Designed and oversaw experiments in a laboratory setting and on a full-scale drill rig.</item>
				<!--<item>Analyzed and interpreted computer, laboratory, and drill rig data.</item>
				<item>Developed software to post process a variety of disjointed laboratory and computer data types in a standardized, uniform way.</item>-->
			</bulletedlist>
		</description>
    </job>
	
</experience>